A Guide to the Frederic G. Melcher-Robert Frost Collection,
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
- Series V: Correspondence of Frederic G. Melcher with Various Authors and Publishers
  - Dorothy Canfield Fisher regrets that she is unable to accept speaking engagements while her children are still young, 1924-1956, n.d. (Box-folder 5:10)
    Dorothy Canfield Fisher regrets that she is unable to accept speaking engagements while her children are still young and Melcher agrees that for writers to speak is a great imposition on their time although he has seen the benefits of public exposure for the author. He also enjoyed her story "Hats" and found its conclusions applicable to publishing (1924); accepts invitation to the Robert Frost dinner, and says, "I'd have been outrageously disappointed to have missed it" (Mar 3, [1925]); shares that she did not enjoy writing Her Son's Wife [1926?]; thanks Melcher for his thoughtful and reassuring words about her last book [Why Stop Learning?] and expresses her concern over the health of Marjorie Frost (Jan 6, 11, 1928); recommends that Americans make much greater use of the Encyclopedia in their everyday questions and disputes (Dec 31, 1934); asks for extra copies of Publisher's Weekly with its excellent photographs of the Skinner Award dinner so she can send them to her friends overseas (1951); thanks Melcher for promising to send her Volume III of the Bowker lectures and mentions that the University of Vermont has been collecting her papers for the last ten years. She also tells of selecting some of her short stories from the last fifty years for publication by Harcourt, Brace and Company (March 4, 1956); and Melcher replies about the importance of collecting the papers of writers, mentioning some of hers in his collection, as well as two favorite photographs of Fisher which are present in this folder (March 8, 1956). In her undated correspondence, she mentions the death of her father-in-law just prior to her speaking engagement at Montclair and the need to borrow a copy of her book Hillsboro People for her reading; and mentions the illness of Marjorie Frost.
  - Esther Forbes expresses her delight that Melcher liked Paradise [1937]; and Rainbow (1954). [1937], 1954 (Box-folder 5:11)
  - Waldo Frank accepts invitation to the Robert Frost dinner. 1925 Mar 10 (Box-folder 5:12)
  - Justice Felix Frankfurter thanks Melcher for the gift of a book, 1949 Feb 10 (Box-folder 5:13)
    Justice Felix Frankfurter thanks Melcher for the gift of a book and says, "Particularly as to things of the mind and spirit, which includes manifestations of beauty, I do not want this country to lag behind any other."
  - Frances Frost regrets that she is unable to be a speaker at the New York Library Association convention due to prior commitments. 1934 Jun 14 (Box-folder 5:14)
  - Ruth G. Gagliardo discusses the upcoming auction, 1956 Jan 17, 25 (Box-folder 5:15)
    Ruth G. Gagliardo discusses the upcoming auction and her success in getting Robert Frost to write out his poem, Pasture and sign it for the auction. She also shares his note praising his great friend, Fred Melcher.
  - Richard Le Gallienne to Charles E. Lauriat, n.d. (Box-folder 5:16)
    Richard Le Gallienne to Charles E. Lauriat, expects to be able to send a large paper copy of his [Odes from the Divan of Hafiz?] within a fortnight.
  - John Galsworthy is pleased with the printing of the article in Publisher's Weekly. 1925 Jun 23 (Box-folder 5:17)
  - Lewis Gannett, New York Herald Tribune, 1956 Oct 2 (Box-folder 5:18)
    Says that the book business would not be such pleasant company without Melcher and that he hopes that he himself has at least twenty more years to do the things that can't be done in the confines of a daily newspaper column.
  - Hamlin Garland hopes that Melcher will join The Town Hall Club, New York. 1925 Mar 21 (Box-folder 5:19)
  - Porter Garnett thanks Melcher for his kind words last Wednesday night. 1932 Feb 3 (Box-folder 5:20)
  - Lillian M. Gilbreth recommends Mary Peters by Mary Ellen Chase as a worthy book to read. 1935 Jan 3 (Box-folder 5:21)
  - Eric Gill complains that the edition of Troilus and Cressida produced by Random House was not produced in consultation with Gill, 1933 Mar 17 & 30, Apr 7 (Box-folder 5:22)
    Eric Gill complains that the edition of Troilus and Cressida produced by Random House was not produced in consultation with Gill and not in accordance with the conditions stipulated by Mr. Gibbings of the Golden Cockerel Press. He was also upset that the decorations were not printed from his wood engravings but from photographic reproductions on a smaller scale and without monetary recompense.
  - Edna M. Glau[?] writes a personal letter to Mrs. Melcher mentioning Daniel Melcher, 1919 Dec 27 (Box-folder 5:23)
  - Frederic W. Goudy sends Melcher a drawing via his wife, 1919, 1929 (Box-folder 5:24)
    Frederic W. Goudy sends Melcher a drawing via his wife as he is laid up with acute indigestion (1919) and he agrees to serve on the Fifty Books Committee to select fifty books for the yearly show of the American Institute of Graphic Arts (1929).
  - Edward Grabhorn appreciates Melcher's praise about the Walt Whitman book. 1930 Sep 3, 30 (Box-folder 5:25)
  - Charles R. Green, Librarian, The Jones Library, Amherst, Massachusetts, chiefly corresponds with Melcher, 1933-1962 (Box-folder 5:26)
    Charles R. Green, Librarian, The Jones Library, Amherst, Massachusetts, chiefly corresponds with Melcher about various aspects of the Robert Frost collection the library is trying to build, including the pursuit of various Frost related items that they lack, a Frost bibliography, Frost chronology and notification of new Frost publications. Occasionally, Green offers Melcher the opportunity to purchase duplicate Frost related items, such as photographs, made available to the library. He also discusses a planned exhibit on the work of Helen Gentry (1939); the purchase of the Robert Frost portrait for the special collection of Robert Frost material in the library (Mar 19, 1942); invitation for Robert Frost's 70th Birthday at the P.E.N. Club Dinner (Mar 13, 1945); request for Melcher to donate some of his material to the library (Jan 17, 21, 1947); honorary degrees given to Frost (May 14, 1947, see list in Box 2); the difference in cost between the American and English Masque of Reason (Dec 24, 1948); request for help in revising their published edition of the Robert Frost Bibliography (Aug 31, 1950; Mar 2, 1955); the Kenyon College Robert Frost celebration (Sep 8, 1950); dedication of the Robert Frost Room (Oct 20, 1958; Oct 27, 1959).
  - Ralph Green discusses Melcher's comments in Notes on Printing and Graphic Arts, 1953 Mar 18, 19 (Box-folder 5:27)
    Ralph Green discusses Melcher's comments in Notes on Printing and Graphic Arts concerning Daniel Fowle's press, and lists the possible wooden presses made before 1787, the date of Fowle's death, that may have been exhibited as the Fowle press in the 19th century.
  - Berta and Elmer S. Hader thank Melcher for his nice letter about their book, n.d. (Box-folder 5:28)
  - Edward E. Hale autograph with the words, "Do the best you can." 1899 Dec 25 (Box-folder 5:29)
  - Alfred Harcourt, Henry Holt and Company, tells Melcher, currently working for W.K. Stewart Company, Indianapolis, Indiana, about the visit of Robert Frost, 1916, 1953 (Box-folder 5:30)
    Alfred Harcourt, Henry Holt and Company, tells Melcher, currently working for W.K. Stewart Company, Indianapolis, Indiana, about the visit of Robert Frost who was very pleased with what he had to say about North of Boston and A Boy's Will in The Publisher's Weekly, with a typescript copy of the column (1916); and appreciates his editorial about Harcourt and Carl Sandburg (1953).
  - Joel Chandler Harris writes a brief note, n.d. (Box-folder 5:31)
    "My vote is always for boys and girls."
  - Albert L. Hartman, Watchung School, 1933 Sep 12 (Box-folder 5:32)
    Thanks Melcher for his letter of commendation for the school.
  - Dr. Victor G. Heiser thanks Mrs. Melcher for her hospitality during his visit. 1938 Oct 21 (Box-folder 5:33)
  - Alice Corbin Henderson writes concerning the growth of Santa Fe, New Mexico and Spanish folk-songs (Oct 7, 1926), 1926-1930 (Box-folder 5:34)
    Discusses the publication of her New Mexico poetry anthology, The Turquoise Trail, and her column "Santa Fe Bookshelf" which appeared in Publisher's Weekly of June 11, 1927 (Jan 2 and Feb 6, 1928); Melcher gives her permission to reprint her column "Santa Fe Bookshelf" (Feb 14, 1928); and notes that both publishers and authors are becoming much more Southwest conscious, citing examples (May 12, 1930).
  - Thomas Wentworth Higginson offers to sell his eight volume set of Winsor's History of America to Messrs. Lauriat & Company. 1907 Feb 16 (Box-folder 5:35)
  - John Haynes Holmes recommends John Stuart Mill's Liberty to the new post-war generation to learn the lessons of liberty anew. 1935 Jan 2 (Box-folder 5:36)
  - Henry Holt and Company, Mr. Holt is unable to attend Frost's birthday dinner (1925) 1925-1954 (Box-folder 5:37)
    Plans for their book on Frost to contain mainly critical studies or reviews of particular books (Aug 11, 1937); sends holiday greeting cards containing printed poems of Robert Frost, Carpe Diem, and The Gift Outright and invites Melcher to both the 70th and 80th birthday celebrations.
  - Herbert Hoover accepts the suggestion made by Mr. Howell to the American Booksellers Association (1929), 1929-1930 (Box-folder 5:38)
    Invites Melcher to be a delegate to the White house Conference on Child Health and Protection (1930)
  - George Wren Howard, Jonathan Cape Limited, London, describes the visit of Robert Frost to their offices and a subsequent party given for him. 1957 Jun 13, 17 (Box-folder 5:39)
  - Henry Hoyns, Harper and Brothers, 1944 Dec 18, Believes no one has "earned more from the publishing business than you [Melcher] have." (Box-folder 5:40)
  - Dard Hunter asks Melcher's opinion about the feasibility of Hunter revising William Edwin Rudge's Papermaking through Eighteen Centuries and selling it at a price that students could afford. 1941 Apr 11, 14 (Box-folder 5:41)
  - Fannie Hurst tells Melcher to contact her manager about a possible speaking engagement in Montclair, New Jersey. 1924 Oct 23, 25 (Box-folder 5:42)
  - Indianapolis Literary Club notifies Melcher of his election to the club. 1917 Nov 30 (Box-folder 5:43)
  - Inez Haynes Irwin has forwarded the dollar he sent on to Mrs. Basnett of the Bundle Shop, although tempted in this present financial crisis to keep it herself. 1933 Mar 13 (Box-folder 5:44)
  - Mitsuru and Michi Ishii, 1947-1948 (Box-folder 5:45)
    A Japanese couple that Melcher met on a trip to Japan about publishing, with the husband being the president of the Japan Publishers Association and his wife the principal of a private school. They write about how his remarks were well received by Japanese educators, publishers, and book dealers and his pursuit of Whitman material. Also present is a letter from the Japanese translator, Tetsuko K. Suzuki, also the sister-in-law of Mr. Ishii.
  - Sarah Orne Jewett to Messrs. Charles E. Lauriat Company, 1902 Jan (Box-folder 5:46)
    Requesting they send her the six volumes of correspondence of George Sand and the Historic de la Dentelle from their last catalog of fine old French books.
  - James Weldon Johnson regrets he is unable to dine with the Melchers on December 27th, 1936 Dec 18 (Box-folder 5:47)
    James Weldon Johnson regrets he is unable to dine with the Melchers on December 27th because he had already accepted another invitation from Mr. and Mrs. David H. Stevens but asks if he can drop in for a few minutes before starting back to New York.
  - Robert Josephy thanks Melcher for his generous gift, 1941 Mar 16 (Box-folder 5:48)
    obert Josephy thanks Melcher for his generous gift and equally generous remarks on Wednesday evening at the Guild party and for his help in his numerous undertakings of the last twenty years.
  - Helen Keller thanks Melcher for his response to her appeal on behalf of the American Foundation for the Blind, Inc. 1946 Feb 6 (Box-folder 5:49)
  - Harry Kemp (1883-1960) describes his book, The Golden Word, [1930?] (Box-folder 5:50)
    Harry Kemp (1883-1960) describes his book, The Golden Word, on sale for two dollars through his printer, N. Berstein, "There are five hundred copies and each one is personally inscribed with my autograph and with a poem of mine."
  - Henry Watson Kent lists the eight hosts for a dinner as himself, Melcher, Silve, Rollins, Rogers, Ruzicka, Cleland, and Warde (1928), 1928, [1940] (Box-folder 5:51)
    Henry Watson Kent lists the eight hosts for a dinner as himself, Melcher, Silve, Rollins, Rogers, Ruzicka, Cleland, and Warde (1928); and is pleased that Melcher had undertaken the chairmanship of the 500th Anniversary of Printing Committee [1940].
  - T[homas] W. Lamont is unable at present to answer Melcher's request for his book preferences. 1934 Dec 31 (Box-folder 5:52)
  - "Jerry" Land (Emory Scott Land) hopes that the debate and vindication vote in the Senate will clear the atmosphere and be advantageous to the [United States Maritime] Commission and staff (1943); and thanks Melcher for his letter about his promotion to Vice Admiral (1944). 1943-1944 (Box-folder 5:53)
  - Julius J. Lankes asks which of his woodcuts appeared in Publisher's Weekly, 1925, 1930, 1932, n.d. (Box-folder 5:54)
    Julius J. Lankes asks which of his woodcuts appeared in Publisher's Weekly and Melcher replies that it was one provided by Doubleday, Page & Company who used the cover for Barren Ground in an advertisement; he also mentions his visit with Robert Frost, who has a display of Lankes prints in his dining room (1925); thanks him for his letter which he will give to the man who issued Virginia Woodcuts; Lankes also complains about people who order books but then never pay for them (1930). Also included are examples of prints by J.J. Lankes.
  - Henry Goddard Leach (1880-1970), 1935 Jan 4 (Box-folder 5:55)
    Henry Goddard Leach (1880-1970), editor of The Forum suggests that Americans should be re-reading Leaves of Grass, "Re-reading Whitman gives the public a sense of the grandeur of the national as well as the authenticity of the meticulous, and here and there a new national poet might spring into being."
  - [Ann?] Leighton to Mr. and Mrs. Melcher, n.y. Jul 17 (Box-folder 5:56)
    Hopes to meet them soon while she is staying at Wellfleet.
  - Josiah K. Lilly, Jr. thanks Melcher for his copies of The Old Wives' Tale and Robert Frost's, Two Tramps in Mud-Time. 1948 Nov 18 (Box-folder 5:57)
  - Joseph C. Lincoln suggests that his talk at Montclair, New Jersey be on "The Making of a Book" discussing how an author gets his material, prepares the story, etc., but agrees to do his Cape Cod talk again at Melcher's request. 1923 Jan-Feb (Box-folder 5:58)
  - Joseph Wharton Lippincott thanks Melcher for his complimentary editorial about the company in Publisher's Weekly. 1941 May 27 (Box-folder 5:59)
  - Hugh Lofting on a postcard discusses the League of Nations in Geneva, 1923 Sep 10 (Box-folder 5:60)
    Hugh Lofting on a postcard discusses the League of Nations in Geneva, facetiously stating that he has been trying to get the Animal Kingdom admitted but everyone is too worked up over the Italian-Greek affair that they won't listen to him.
  - Nicholas Longworth to Cass Canfield, Harper and Brothers, 1930 May 26 (Box-folder 5:61)
    Reports on the progress of H.R. 6990, reintroduced as H.R. 12549.
  - Milton Edward Lord, Director of the Boston Public Library, 1956 Oct 5 (Box-folder 5:62)
    Found Melcher's, A Boston Bookstore at the Turn of the Century fascinating.
  - Amy Lowell arranges a day for a talk at Montclair, New Jersey, 1919 Jul-Dec (Box-folder 5:63)
    Amy Lowell arranges a day for a talk at Montclair, New Jersey, around the dates of her Columbia lectures in New York and the topic, preferring a reading of her poems with explanatory remarks. She later thanks Melcher for his hospitality and the clipping from Publisher's Weekly about her book [Pictures of the Floating World ?].
  - Robert Luce, U.S. House of Representatives, Chairman of the Committee on the Library, thanks Melcher for his note and a book. 1931 Jan 26 (Box-folder 5:64)
  - H. M. Lydenberg, Director of the New York Public Library, 1935 Jan 4 (Box-folder 5:65)
    Recommends, "For a stimulant, a delight, a book with constant and certain appeal, a book of lasting and perennial charm, an invitation to appreciation of idealism, a constant demonstration of the necessity of balance, a responsive mirror of human nature, give me the book from the pen of that charming, stimulating, revealing, gratitude-provoking Cid Hamlet Benengeli transcribed by Cervantes as "Don Quixote."
  - Arthur Machen (1863-1947), 1923-1924 (Box-folder 5:66)
    Arthur Machen (1863-1947) gives permission to use his article The Collector's Craft for a fee of fifteen dollars and expresses his surprise that Hieroglyphics a Note Upon Ecstasy in Literature is doing well in the United States (1923).
  - Percy MacKaye and his daughter, Arvia, will be happy to come to Robert Frost's dinner. 1925 Feb 27, Mar 4 (Box-folder 5:67)
  - Archibald MacLeish states that he is unable to come to the conference although he knows how important it is (August 9, 1939), 1939-1945 (Box-folder 5:68)
    Tries to gauge the usefulness of a conference on the Copyright Act (August 21,1943); and appreciates the statement on international aspects of the use of books from Melcher for use in the United Nations conference to be called in London (May 24, 1945).
  - John Macrae, Chairman of the Nominating Committee of the National Association of Book Publishers, writes concerning Melcher's nomination for the post of Secretary. 1932 Nov 28, 30 (Box-folder 5:69)
  - Thomas R. Marshall, Vice-President of the United States, to W.K. Stewart Company, Indianapolis, Indiana, 1917 Dec 1 (Box-folder 5:70)
    Asks for two copies of the Lincoln Anthology and one copy of Charles W. Moore's Life of Lincoln.
  - Walter S. Marvin, Secretary of the Montclair Art Museum, 1940 Mar 5 (Box-folder 5:71)
    Expressing the deep regret with which the Board received Melcher's resignation from the Board of Trustees and their deep appreciation for his many services.
  - Jan Masaryk says he is unable to come to Montclair and speak at this time as he must sail on the Queen Elizabeth in two days. 1947 Jan 16, 17 (Box-folder 5:72)
  - John Masefield shares the origin of his verse-speaking festivals, 1928-1931, 1957 Aug 10, 14, n.d. (Box-folder 5:73)
    John Masefield shares the origin of his verse-speaking festivals, 1928-1931, and the founding of the Scottish Association for the Speaking of Verse around 1922. Melcher shares his memory of taking Nicholas Vachel Lindsay to hear Masefield speak before a club he belonged to in Indiana.
  - William Babington Maxwell, a delegate from the Society of Authors, 1923 Jun-Oct (Box-folder 5:74)
    Regrets having to sail for home without meeting with Melcher again.
  - Frederic G. Melcher sends a form letter, 1934 Dec 28 (Box-folder 5:75)
    Frederic G. Melcher sends a form letter posing the question, "What would be your one-book prescription for country-wide 'required' reading for this coming year?" This was sent to a hundred people for their response, and several respondents' correspondence is in this series under their names.
  - Frederic G. Melcher to Thomas P. Stricker, 1935 Oct 15 (Box-folder 5:76)
    Asking for his participation on the Fifty Books Committee of the American Institute of Graphic Arts.
  - Frederic G. Melcher writing home from Spokane, Washington, n.d. (Box-folder 5:77)
    Mentions Vachel Lindsay's meeting with Hoddard King, a visit to the library, an interview with the press, a visit with the Lindsays to see the baby, all on his first day's visit to Spokane.
  - H.L. Mencken agrees to speak at the American Booksellers Association luncheon, 1940, 1946, n.d. (Box-folder 5:78)
    H.L. Mencken agrees to speak at the American Booksellers Association luncheon on the topic of the future of the book and Melcher sends several suggestions for avenues to explore. Mencken's five- page typescript carbon for that talk delivered on May 13, 1940, is present with his correspondence (1940): and in two undated notes arranges for the printing of two different articles.
  - Elliott Merrick ("Bud") writes concerning the harsh winter and the sale of his book, From This Hill (February 10, 1935), 1935-1942, n.d. (Box-folder 5:79)
    Elliott Merrick ("Bud") writes concerning the harsh winter and the sale of his book, From This Hill (February 10, 1935); says some of his work will appear in Story in December and asks Melcher to write a letter recommending him for a Guggenheim Fellowship (October 28, November 1, 1935); describes writing a book, "It seems to me rather like putting on a diver's helmet and going down to the bottom of the ocean, with no respite for a year except an occasional attack of the bends by way of relaxation" (August 11, [1936]); gives his reaction to the advance copy of R.F.D. sent by Melcher (March 7, [1938?]; describes the good results from his Mohonk trip concerning Frost and Fire and his concern over Melcher's health (September 1939) which turned out to be an attack of appendicitis October 5, [1939]; his trip to Labrador during the summer, purchase of a sailboat and the progress in sales of Northern Nurse (January 4, 1942); describes their vacation stay at the Melchers' at Wellfleet, Massachusetts (August 1, 5, 19, 29, n.y.); and explains his new job as Southeastern Forest Experiment Station editor at Asheville, North Carolina (October 12, n.y.).
  - Sir Francis Meynell, The Nonesuch Press Ltd., 1930 Aug 22 (Box-folder 5:80)
    Thanks Melcher for his kind words about his Keepsake.
  - Carl H. Milam thanks Melcher for the gift to the American Library Association building fund in his honor. 1961 Feb 7 (Box-folder 5:81)
  - Alan Alexander Milne, from Melcher, 1947, 1953 (Box-folder 5:82)
    Alan Alexander Milne, from Melcher who shares his experience in Japan with the publisher Mitsuru Ishii and his wife, who had seen their school and home destroyed by incendiaries during World War II. Mr. Ishii lost his entire collection of 10,000 books, and Mrs. Suzuki, about 1,000 children's books but she did manage to save one because it was hidden in a dugout in the school yard. It was the Methuen edition of When We Were Very Young. Milne says that he wrote to Mrs. Suzuki and discusses his work used in Japanese school books. He also talks about his son's career at Cambridge in a news clipping mentioned by Melcher. (1947). Melcher then wrote Milne in 1953, telling Milne that he related the same story at a convention of children's librarians who then asked him to read The King's Breakfast. This became a tradition with Melcher telling the story and reading "The King's Breakfast" to the librarians every year.
  - Margaret Mitchell writes about the Berne Convention treaty in the Senate, 1939, 1941 (Box-folder 5:83)
    legislation in Congress to provide real copyright protection for American authors abroad, and her problem with the Dutch courts (1939). She also thanks Melcher for sending her the Publisher's Weekly story, "Dutch Court Gives Ruling in Mitchell Case" (1941).
  - Silas Weir Mitchell autograph signed at Bar Harbor, Maine n.d. (Box-folder 5:84)
  - Harriet Monroe regrets that she is unable to attend the Robert Frost birthday dinner, 1925 Mar 16 (Box-folder 5:85)